Caffè Lena collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
Caffè Lena collection 1960-2013
AFC 2009/035
Caffè Lena Board of Directors
7767 items
28 containers
12 linear feet
42 sound tape reels: analog; 10 in.
46 sound tape reels: analog; 7 in.
5 sound tape reels: analog; 5 in.
1 sound tape reel: analog; 3 in.
381 sound cassettes: analog and digital.
13 videocassettes (VHS): sound only; 1/2 in.
1 sound microcassette: analog.
36 sound discs: digital.
1942 audio files: digital, aiff, mp3, wav
1 videocassette (U-matic): sound, color.
14 videocassettes (VHS): sound, color.
2 videodiscs (DVD-R): digital.
1 film reel (1100 feet): analog.
12 video files: digital, mov, mp4
approximately 1540 photographs: black and white, color; various sizes.
3504 pages.
261 files: digital, pdf, doc
3 objects.
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Collection of more than 500 audio recordings, plus digital audio files, video recordings, film, photographs, papers, and ephemera documenting the history of the Caffè Lena coffeehouse, a folk music club and theater in Saratoga Springs, New York, founded by Lena Spencer and Bill Spencer in 1960. The collection includes a large number of live concert performance recordings by folk musicians and singer-songwriters, as well as some theater, storytelling, and poetry performances. The collection also includes folk music radio programs produced from Caffè Lena concerts by Robert Durand and others. Some materials were gathered by Jocelyn Arem while conducting research on the history of Caffè Lena, and the collection includes drafts and page proofs of Arem's book, Caffè Lena: Inside America's Legendary Folk Music Coffeehouse (2013).
Provenance
Caffè Lena Board of Directors; 2009, 2010, 2013.
Related Material
Caffè Lena History Project
Saratoga Springs History Museum collection of Caffè Lena materials (AFC 2009/034), American Folklife Center, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.
Coffeehouses: folk music, culture and counterculture symposium (AFC 2014/009), American Folklife Center, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.
Access and Restrictions
The Caffè Lena collection is open to research. To request materials, please contact the Folklife Reading Room at https://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/folklife.contact
Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Biographical Note
Lena Spencer (born Pasqualina Rosa Nargi, on January 4, 1923) owned and operated Caffè Lena from its inception in 1960 until her untimely death in 1989. Before she co-founded Caffè Lena in 1960 with her then-husband Bill Spencer, she gained experience that would bear fruit during her long years at Caffè Lena as both owner and jack of all trades: she waited tables at her father's Italian restaurant, performed with an amateur theater group, and worked at a radio station. Over the years she built a reputation for the Caffè as the place for serious folk artists to play. The Caffè had a loyal following over the years, who periodically helped raise funds to keep the business open. Despite her passing, the Caffè has continued to be a destination venue for folk music artists and fans of folk music: "good folk since 1960."
Scope and Content
Collection of more than 500 audio recordings, plus digital audio files, video recordings, film, photographs, papers, and ephemera documenting the history of the Caffè Lena coffeehouse, a folk music club and theater in Saratoga Springs, New York, founded by Lena Spencer and Bill Spencer in 1960. The collection includes a large number of live concert performance recordings by folk musicians and singer-songwriters, as well as some theater, storytelling, and poetry performances. The collection also includes folk music radio programs produced from Caffè Lena concerts by Robert Durand and others. Some materials were gathered by Jocelyn Arem while conducting research on the history of Caffè Lena, and the collection includes drafts and page proofs of Arem's book, Caffè Lena: Inside America's Legendary Folk Music Coffeehouse (2013).
Arrangement
Materials in The Caffè Lena collection are described in the finding aid according to intellectual arrangement rather than numbering sequence (with particular regard to sound recordings). They are organized by format into the following series:
Series 1: Manuscripts
Series 2: Sound Recordings
Series 3: Graphic Images
Series 4: Moving Images
Series 5: Artifacts
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Alper, Joe, 1925-1968; Amram, David; Arem, Jocelyn; Armstrong, Frankie; Block, Rory; Bok, Gordon; Book Binder, Roy; Bromberg, David, 1945-; Broudy, Saul; Brown, Greg, 1949-; Carawan, Guy; Clements, Vassar; Cooney, Michael B., 1943-; Estes, Sleepy John, 1899-1977; Franke, Bob; Geremia, Paul; Gillette, Steve; Guthrie, Arlo; Hills, Anne; Lavin, Christine; MacArthur, Margaret, 1928-2006; Mangsen, Cindy; McCaslin, Mary; McCutcheon, John, 1952-; McGarrigle, Anna; McGarrigle, Kate; McLean, Don, 1945-; Muir, Ann Mayo; Paton, Caroline; Paton, Sandy; Paxton, Tom, 1937-; Petric, Faith; Pettis, Pierce; Phillips, Utah; Redpath, Jean; Ringer, Jim; Ritchie, Jean; Rogers, Gamble; Rogers, Garnet; Rucker, Sparky; Sciaky, Carla; Seeger, Mike, 1933-2009; Seeger, Pete, 1919-2014; Sky, Patrick; Sorrels, Rosalie; Spencer, Lena, 1923-1989; Spencer, Lena, 1923-1989.; Staines, Bill; Tabor, June; Traum, Artie; Traum, Happy; Van Ronk, Dave; Van Zandt, Townes; Vanaver, Bill; Wakefield, Frank; Walker, Jerry Jeff; West, Hedy
Organizations
Aztec Two-Step (Musical group); Balfa Brothers; Caffè Lena (Saratoga Springs, N.Y.); Caffè Lena (Saratoga Springs, N.Y.); Greenbriar Boys; Schooner Fare (Musical group)
Subjects
Coffeehouses--New York (State)--Saratoga Springs.; Concerts--New York (State)--Saratoga Springs.; Folk music--United States.; Folk musicians--Interviews.; Popular music--1961-1970.; Popular music--1971-1980.; Popular music--1981-1990.; Popular music--1991-2000.; Popular music--2001-2010.
Form/Genre
Ballads.; Blues (Music); Clippings.; Concerts.; Folk music radio programs.; Interviews.; Manuscripts.; Oral histories.; Photographs.; Poems.; Posters.; Recipes.; Scrapbooks.; Songs.; Sound recordings.; Videocassettes.
Container List
- Series 1: Manuscripts
  Digital items received from the donor are not yet processed. The item ID information in the finding aid refers to the physical items, as the digital item IDs are different from the analog item IDs.
  - Subseries 1: History and activities
    - Correspondence (folder 1 of 2), 1989-1991 (Box-folder 1/1)
      Correspondence from various individuals regarding Caffè Lena, its management, and Lena Spencer's legacy.
    - Correspondence (folder 2 of 2), 2001-2007, undated (Box-folder 1/2)
      See note for folder 1/1
    - Correspondence from Dan Stetkar to Jocelyn Arem, 2011-2013 (Box-folder 1/3)
      Printouts of emails and other documents, some of which help identify individuals in photos taken by Joe Alper.
    - Caffè Lena history, circa 1980s (Box-folder 1/4)
      Includes broadcast permission forms for WMHT, a Caffè Lena menu, typed histories of Caffè Lena, newspaper articles, announcements, etc. Photos from this folder, plus a photo ID related to images elsewhere in the collection, have been relocated to the folder "Caffè Lena: history (photos)," in Series 3.
    - Caffè Lena documentary, 1989-1990 (Box-folder 1/5)
      Includes planning documents, notes, contact lists, etc.
    - Recipes collected by Lena Spencer (Box-folder 1/6)
      At least one recipe (from Rosalie Sorrels) was given to Spencer. The rest may be in Spencer's handwriting, and originally hers.
    - Caffè Lena food and beverage menus 1997, undated (Box-folder 1/7)
      Two laminated menus from 1997 and one paper menu (undated).
    - New York State Folk Arts Roundtable, May 19-21, 2010 (Box-folder 1/8)
      Program and related materials
    - Saratoga History Museum: Jocelyn Arem's research notes, May 19-21, 2010 (Box-folder 1/9)
      Photocopies include materials from 1972-1989. Research notes date from circa 2003-2005.
    - The early days of Caffè Lena: the socio-historical identity of an American music venue (copy 1), 2003-2004 (Box-folder 1/10)
      Jocelyn Arem's senior Capstone project at Skidmore College. The velo-bound document is an ethnography and oral history account. Copy 1 has handwritten notes at the back.
    - The early days of Caffè Lena: the socio-historical identity of an American music venue (copy 2), 2003-2004 (Box-folder 1/11)
      See note for folder 1/11.
    - Jocelyn Arem's Caffè Lena project updates and related documentation, 2004-2010 (Box-folder 1/12)
      Letters to the Caffè Lena Board, meeting notes, project goals, etc.
    - Caffè Lena history project: oral history questionnaire, 2005-2006 (Box-folder 1/13)
    - Caffè Lena history project: planning stages, 1999-2006 (Box-folder 2/1)
      Includes names, lists, correspondence, and other documentation.
    - Caffè Lena history exhibit project plan and related documentation, 2004-2009; undated (Box-folder 2/2)
      Includes both plans and Jocelyn Arem's research on other exhibits.
    - Caffè Lena Community Drum Circle (Box-folder 2/3)
      1 flyer, giving the statement of intent, rules, etc.
    - Great Saratoga Music Hall (Box-folder 2/4)
      Photocopies of articles about the reopening of the hall, and related materials. Lena Spencer was one of three people who leased the hall when it reopened.
    - "The Commandant of Auschwitz" (Caffè Lena Theatre production) (Box-folder 2/5)
      A one-page program/summary for the production.
    - "Every drop of water: voices from the Caffè Lena poetry stage," vol. 1, 2008 (Box-folder 2/6)
      A professionally-printed compilation of poems.
    - "Monday is the opposite of Batman," 2011 (Box-folder 2/7)
      Poetry written as part of a workshop held at Caffè Lena in 2011.
  - Subseries 2: Honors
    - Skidmore College commencement exercises program, May 9, 1987 (Box-folder 2/8)
      Skidmore College granted Lena Spencer an honorary Doctor of Humane Letters in 1987.
    - Lena Spencer Award (Box-folder 2/9)
      1 promotional flyer.
    - Caffè Lena Day (May 22, 2010) (Box-folder 2/10)
      Two copies of the proclamation, in presentation folders.
  - Subseries 3: Media coverage, press kits, and publicity
    - Media coverage (folder 1 of 20), 1960-1976 (Box-folder 2/11)
      Includes Caffè Lena newsletters from 1961 and 1962, as well as media coverage regarding performers and the venue itself. A letter to Lena Spencer from Kenneth E. King (commissioner of public safety), dated January 24, 1968, is included. No materials for 1963-1964 and 1969-1970. All materials are photocopies or thermofaxes.
    - Media coverage (folder 2 of 20), 1977-1988 (Box-folder 2/12)
      Includes media coverage for performers and the venue, as well such materials as programs (e.g., "The Mousetrap," staged in 1978, a typed letter from Lena Spencer requesting financial support from friends of Caffè Lena, sent in 1981, a color photocopy of a proclamation declaring May 19, 1985 as Lena Spencer Day in Saratoga Springs, New York, etc.). No materials for 1982. All materials are photocopies.
    - Media coverage (folder 3 of 20), 1989 (Box-folder 2/13)
      Includes media coverage for performers and the venue, as well such materials as a mock-up for the cover of the brochure "Caffè Lena: the second thirty years," and numerous tributes to Lena Spencer. Almost all materials are photocopies, except a few original articles. An original issue of "Eye on Saratoga" has been relocated to box 17 (a photocopy remains in this folder).
    - Media coverage (folder 4 of 20), 1990-1997 (Box-folder 3/1)
      Includes media coverage for performers and the venue, as well such materials as copies of the brochure "Caffè Lena: the second thirty years" and a letter to friends of Caffè Lena announcing it would be sold to a non-profit organization (1990), an original flyer for the 4th annual Caffè Lena Folk-A-Thon (1993), an original issue of Bluegrass (magazine), with an article on Caffè Lena (1993), a copy of the minutes of a 1995 meeting (printed on orange paper), and photocopies of Board meeting minutes (1995). A significant majority of the materials are photocopies.
    - Media coverage (folder 5 of 20), 1998 (Box-folder 3/2)
      Includes tickets, programs, brochures, and other materials, and documentation and publicity related to the fund-raising campaign to buy the building, etc. Contents are a combination of original and duplicated materials. Two ads for the fund-raising event, created on film, have been relocated to Series 3.
    - Media coverage (folder 6 of 20), 1998 (Box-folder 3/3)
      Includes newspaper articles (photocopies and printouts).
    - Media coverage (folder 7 of 20), 1999 (Box-folder 3/4)
      Includes copies of a fax sent to Bernice Johnson Reagon from Abigail Reid, the faxed response from Reagon, photocopies of newspaper clippings, and related materials.
    - Media coverage (folder 8 of 20), 2000 (Box-folder 3/5)
      Includes newspaper clippings (original and photocopies), plus related documentation of Caffè Lena's history, and a printed, general thank you to Caffè Lena supporters.
    - Media coverage (folder 9 of 20), 2001 (Box-folder 3/6)
      Includes newspaper clippings (original and photocopies), a tribute to Alfredo Lombardi, etc.
    - Media coverage (folder 10 of 20), 2002 (Box-folder 3/7)
      Includes newspaper clippings (original and photocopies), a certificate naming Caffè Lena as the best coffeehouse in the Capital Region for 2002, etc.
    - Media coverage (folder 11 of 20), 2003 (Box-folder 3/8)
      Includes newspaper clippings (original and photocopies), etc.
    - Media coverage (folder 12 of 20), 2004 (Box-folder 3/9)
    - Media coverage (folder 13 of 20), 2005 (Box-folder 3/10)
      Includes newspaper clippings (original and photocopies), a laminated menu, a flyer for the production of Two Gentlemen of Verona, etc.
    - Media coverage (folder 14 of 20), 2006 (Box-folder 3/11)
      Includes newspaper clippings (photocopies), promotional materials for various companies, etc.
    - Media coverage (folder 15 of 20), 2007 (Box-folder 3/12)
      Includes newspaper clippings and publications (original and photocopies).
    - Media coverage (folder 16 of 20), 2008 (Box-folder 3/13)
      Includes newspaper clippings (original and a photocopy).
    - Media coverage (folder 17 of 20), 2009 (Box-folder 3/14)
      Includes a copy of a magazine article, two copies of the Poetry Festival program, and two copies of the Chowderfest Chanty Sing.
    - Media coverage (folder 18 of 20), 2010 (Box-folder 3/15)
      Includes articles (one original and one photocopy), a membership flyer for Caffè Lena, and a flyer for a poetry festival.
    - Media coverage (folder 19 of 20), undated (Box-folder 4/1)
      Includes newspaper clippings (photocopies and one original).
    - Media coverage (folder 20 of 20), 2009-2013, undated (Box-folder 4/2)
      Includes original clippings from magazines and newspapers on the 50th anniversary of Caffè Lena. One subfolder of photocopies, submitted to Jocelyn Arem by Joan Kosby and Paul Mercer, have a variety of dates.
    - Publicity materials, circa 1970s (Box-folder 4/3)
      Includes publicity materials for various artists. Photos have been relocated to Series 3; photocopies are in this folder.
    - Quotations and miscellaneous writings, 1972-2007; undated (Box-folder 4/4)
      Includes quotations compiled for publicity as well as writings by people paying tribute both to Lena Spencer and to Caffè Lena.
    - Publicity: meetings, notes, etc. (folder 1 of 2), 1996 (Box-folder 4/5)
    - Publicity: meetings, notes, etc. (folder 2 of 2), circa 1990s (Box-folder 4/6)
    - Caffè Lena, Inc., 1989-1990, undated (Box-folder 4/7)
      Various promotional items, plus a letter to New York Telephone (phone company) informing them of Lena Spencer's death.
    - Lena Spencer's accident and Caffè Lena's future: media coverage (folder 1 of 2), 1989-1991 (Box-folder 4/8)
      Newspaper clippings (original and photocopies). Oversized materials have been relocated to box 17.
    - Lena Spencer's accident and Caffè Lena's future: media coverage (folder 2 of 2), 1989-1991 (Box-folder 4/9)
      See note for 3/8.
    - Caffè Lena's future and the Trust Fund, 1980s, undated (Box-folder 4/10)
    - Memorial service for Lena Spencer, 1989 (Box-folder 4/11)
      Documentation of some parts of the planning phase, plus an announcement flyer, draft of the program, final program, and various notes.
    - Articles written by Jocelyn Arem, 2008 (Box-folder 5/1)
      Two articles, in the original published format: "Lena's Legacy: the lasting power of Caffè Lena, America's oldest continuously running folk coffeehouse," North Carolina Folklore Journal, 55, no. 1 (Spring-Summer 2008): 17-31, and "Forty-seven Years at 47 Phila Street: America's oldest continuously running folk coffeehouse," Voices: the Journal of New York Folklore, 34, nos. 1-2 (Spring-Summer 2008): 12-18. Jocelyn Arem is the historian for Caffè Lena.
  - Subseries 4: Caffè Lena: Inside America's Legendary Folk Music Coffeehouse
    - Book project overview (Box-folder 5/2)
      Spiral-bound and index-tabbed; includes mock-ups, book and exhibit proposal, etc.
    - Caffè Lena's history (folder 1 of 2), 2008-2011 (Box-folder 5/3)
      Includes early proposals and drafts, revisions, etc.
    - Caffè Lena's history (folder 2 of 2), 2008-2011 (Box-folder 5/4)
      See note for folder 1/17.
    - Mock-ups (folder 1 of 2), 2010-2013 (Box-folder 5/5)
      Also includes Jocelyn Arem's handwritten notes.
    - Mock-ups (folder 2 of 2), 2010-2013 (Box-folder 5/6)
      See note for folder 1/19.
    - Page proofs (folder 1 of 2) (Box-folder 5/7)
    - Page proofs (folder 2 of 2) (Box-folder 5/8)
  - Subseries 5: Artist files
    - Ad-At (Box-folder 6/1)
    - Austin, Hattie (Box-folder 6/2)
    - Ba-Bro (Box-folder 6/3)
    - Bruchac, Joe (Box-folder 6/4)
    - Bu (Box-folder 6/5)
    - C (Box-folder 6/6)
    - D (Box-folder 6/7)
    - E (Box-folder 6/8)
    - F (Box-folder 6/9)
    - G (Box-folder 6/10)
    - H (Box-folder 6/11)
    - K (Box-folder 6/12)
    - L (Box-folder 6/13)
    - McKenney, Al (Box-folder 6/14)
    - McLean, Don (Box-folder 7/1)
    - M (Box-folder 7/2)
    - N-O (Box-folder 7/3)
    - Phillips, Utah (Box-folder 7/4)
    - P (Box-folder 7/5)
    - Reagon, Bernice Johnson (Box-folder 7/6)
    - Robbins, Gil (Tim and David) (Box-folder 7/7)
    - R (Box-folder 7/8)
    - Sorrels, Rosalie (Box-folder 7/9)
    - Spencer, Lena (folder 1 of 2) (Box-folder 7/10)
    - Spencer, Lena (folder 2 of 2) (Box-folder 7/11)
    - S (Box-folder 8/1)
    - T (Box-folder 8/2)
    - U-V (Box-folder 8/3)
    - Ward, George (Box-folder 8/4)
    - W (Box-folder 8/5)
  - Subseries 6: Newsletters, performance calendars, and related materials
    - Newsletters, calendars, and promotional materials, 1995-2009, undated (Box-folder 9/1)
      Various venues, including Caffè Lena.
    - Caffè Lena newsletters, 1995-2005 (Box-folder 9/2)
      This newsletter was originally titled Riffs from Lena's. All are original except as noted. Newsletter issues here include: October 1995 (#6; 3 copies), July 1996 (#6, possibly numbered in error; 3 copies), December 1997 (#9), April 1998 (#10), October 1998 (#12), January 1999 (#14), April 1999 (#15; 2 copies), November 12, 1998 (#17), February 22, 1999 (#18), July 2000 (#20; 2 copies), January 2004 (no issue number; photocopy).
    - Caffè Lena performance calendars (folder 1 of 3), 1990-2002 (Box-folder 9/3)
      Original documents, with a few photocopies. Also includes two handwritten notes, to "Sarah" from an unidentified person, and a handwritten list of calendar payments received. From the original folder "Caffè Lena Calendars, 1990-2009."
    - Caffè Lena performance calendars (folder 2 of 3), 2003-November 2010 (Box-folder 9/4)
      From the original folder "Caffè Lena Calendars, 1990-2009."
    - Caffè Lena performance calendars (folder 3 of 3), December 2010-May 2012 (Box-folder 9/5)
      See note for folder 9/4.
    - Caffè Lena membership drive, 1996-1997 (Box-folder 9/6)
    - Web site printout, 1998, 2009 (Box-folder 9/7)
      Early version of the Caffè Lena web site.
    - Programs, posters, art work, calendars, etc., circa 2009-2010 (Box-folder 9/8)
    - Caffè Lena 50th anniversary: programs and miscellaneous materials, circa 2010 (Box-folder 10/1)
    - Set lists, 2006, undated (Box-folder 10/2)
      Two set lists: one from March 5, 2006; the other undated.
    - Forms to confirm receipt of submitted audition materials (Box-folder 10/3)
      Two items.
    - Audience questionnaire, 1997 (Box-folder 10/4)
      Food service survey to determine attendee preference for a one-waitress or two-waitress service system, including instructions provided for the waitresses.
  - Subseries 7: Other publications
    - Hootenanny, November 9, 1963. (Box-folder 10/5)
    - Lullaby and other songs, 1968. (Box-folder 10/6)
      Pamphlet of published works by Guy MacKenzie.
    - Conspiracy manual, circa 1974. (Box-folder 10/7)
      Planning document for activities to raise funds for Caffè Lena, without Lena Spencer's knowledge.
    - Fast Folk: 25th anniversary CD project, September 1985. (Box-folder 10/8)
      Photocopy of issue featuring a story on the 25th anniversary of Caffè Lena; related documentation accompanies the issue.
    - Folk Times, 1995-1996, 1999, 2002-2005, 2008-2009. (Box-folder 10/9)
      Issues spanning these years.
    - Old Vienna Kaffehaus and Restaurant calendar, November-December 1989. (Box-folder 10/10)
      Four copies of a flyer for upcoming events, which includes an announcement for a benefit concert for Lena Spencer.
    - Lively Lucy's Coffeehouse (Skidmore College), 1992-2003 (Box-folder 10/11)
      Correspondence and press coverage regarding the reopening of Lively Lucy's.
  - Subseries 8: Finances, bills, and management
    - Expenses (folder 1 of 12), January 1996 (Box-folder 11/1)
      Expenses and related documentation.
    - Expenses (folder 2 of 12), February 1996 (Box-folder 11/2)
      See note for folder 11/1.
    - Expenses (folder 3 of 12), March 1996 (Box-folder 11/3)
      See note for 11/1.
    - Expenses (folder 4 of 12), April 1996 (Box-folder 11/4)
    - Expenses (folder 5 of 12), May 1996 (Box-folder 11/5)
    - Expenses (folder 6 of 12), June 1996 (Box-folder 11/6)
    - Expenses (folder 7 of 12), July 1996 (Box-folder 11/7)
    - Expenses (folder 8 of 12), August 1996 (Box-folder 11/8)
    - Expenses (folder 9 of 12), September 1996 (Box-folder 11/9)
    - Expenses (folder 10 of 12), October 1996 (Box-folder 11/10)
    - Expenses (folder 11 of 12), November 1996 (Box-folder 11/11)
    - Expenses (folder 12 of 12), December 1996 (Box-folder 11/12)
    - Adirondack Trust Co.: form letters, circa 1990 (Box-folder 11/13)
    - Sales tax, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 11/14)
      Tax documents, payment requests, and related documentation.
    - Bills to pay and various tasks, 1989-1990, undated (Box-folder 11/15)
      Notes, correspondence, etc.
    - Medical bills and Medicare documents for Lena Spencer, 1989-1990, undated (Box-folder 11/16)
      Includes handwritten notes on the documents, as well as separate, handwritten documents.
    - Bookkeeping for Caffè Lena (1 of 2), 1989-1990 (Box-folder 12/1)
      Documentation, including tax papers and handwritten notes, and balance sheets for Caffè Lena Trust Fund.
    - Bookkeeping for Caffè Lena (folder 2 of 2), 1989-1990 (Box-folder 12/2)
      See note for folder 12/2.
    - Payroll, 1989-1991, undated (Box-folder 12/3)